A Guide to the Papers of James Monroe 1778-1831
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Monroe 1778-1831
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
: Multiple numbers
This collection consists of ca. 209 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase. See individual accession numbers for more information.
Biographical/Historical Information
Fifth President 1817-1825; born April 28, 1758 in Westmoreland County, Virginia; married, Elizabeth Kortright (1768-1830) February 16, 1786; children: Eliza Kortright Monroe (1786-1835), James Spence Monroe (1799-1800), Maria Hester Monroe (1803-1850); died July 4, 1831 in New York, New York; buried: Hollywood Cemetery, Richmond, Virginia.
Born in Westmoreland County, Virginia, in 1758, Monroe attended the College of William and Mary, fought with distinction in the Continental Army, and practiced law in Fredericksburg, Virginia.
As a youthful politician, he joined the anti-Federalists in the Virginia Convention which ratified the Constitution, and in 1790, an advocate of Jeffersonian policies, was elected United States Senator. As Minister to France in 1794-1796, he displayed strong sympathies for the French cause; later, with Robert R. Livingston, he helped negotiate the Louisiana Purchase. His ambition and energy, together with the backing of President Madison, made him the Republican choice for the Presidency in 1816. With little Federalist opposition, he easily won re-election in 1820. Monroe made unusually strong Cabinet choices, naming a Southerner, John C. Calhoun, as Secretary of War, and a northerner, John Quincy Adams, as Secretary of State. Only Henry Clay's refusal kept Monroe from adding an outstanding Westerner.
Early in his administration, Monroe undertook a goodwill tour. At Boston, his visit was hailed as the beginning of an "Era of Good Feelings." Unfortunately these "good feelings" did not endure, although Monroe, his popularity undiminished, followed nationalist policies.
Across the facade of nationalism, ugly sectional cracks appeared. A painful economic depression undoubtedly increased the dismay of the people of the Missouri Territory in 1819 when their application for admission to the Union as a slave state failed. An amended bill for gradually eliminating slavery in Missouri precipitated two years of bitter debate in Congress. The Missouri Compromise bill resolved the struggle, pairing Missouri as a slave state with Maine, a free state, and barring slavery north and west of Missouri forever.
In foreign affairs Monroe proclaimed the fundamental policy that bears his name, responding to the threat that the more conservative governments in Europe might try to aid Spain in winning back her former Latin American colonies. Monroe did not begin formally to recognize the young sister republics until 1822, after ascertaining that Congress would vote appropriations for diplomatic missions. He and Secretary of State John Quincy Adams wished to avoid trouble with Spain until it had ceded the Floridas, as was done in 1821.
Great Britain, with its powerful navy, also opposed reconquest of Latin America and suggested that the United States join in proclaiming "hands off." Ex-Presidents Jefferson and Madison counseled Monroe to accept the offer, but Secretary Adams advised, "It would be more candid ... to avow our principles explicitly to Russia and France, than to come in as a cock-boat in the wake of the British man-of-war."
Monroe accepted Adams's advice. Not only must Latin America be left alone, he warned, but also Russia must not encroach southward on the Pacific coast. "... the American continents," he stated, "by the free and independent condition which they have assumed and maintain, are henceforth not to be considered as subjects for future colonization by any European Power." Some 20 years after Monroe died in 1831, this became known as the Monroe Doctrine.
Scope and Content
The Papers of James Monroe (ca. 209 items) consist chiefly of correspondence with friends, family members, and fellow politicians.
Contents List
- James Monroe to an unidentified General 1778 September, ALS, 4 p. on 2 l.; includes transcript and photocopy; damaged; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7224
- James Monroe to Richard Henry Lee 1781 November 4, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf l.; remnant of wax seal. (Box 1)
  #38-112
- James Monroe to Mrs. James Hunter 1783 January 26, ALS, 2 p. on 2 l., photocopy. (Box 1)
  Original in the Hitchcock-Coit Collection of Mills College Library. #5957
- James Monroe to [John Francis Mercer?] 1783 August 8, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf (fragment); docketed; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8991
- James Monroe to [Wilson Cary Nicholas] [ca. 1783], ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #5533
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1785 January 11, ALS, 1 p.; summary included. (Box 1)
  #6106
- Land Grant, Patrick Henry to James Monroe 1786 May 18, DS, 1 p. with address leaf; photocopy. (Box 1)
  #7716-l
- James Monroe power of attorney to Harry Heth 1788 January 6, ADS, 2 p. on 1 l.; silked. (Box 1)
  #38-114
- James Monroe to [Larkin Standard?] 1788 April 7, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4476
- James Monroe to [Nicholas] Lewis 1791 February 7, ALS, 2 p. on 2 l.; photocopy. Original privately owned. (Box 1)
  #3419
- Indenture for sale 3 lots in Charlottesville by James Monroe 1791 September 26, DS, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #10398-a
- James Monroe to St. George Tucker 1792 January 24, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #7262
- James Monroe to Tench Coxe 1792 April 13, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
  #1661
- James Monroe to St. George Tucker 1794 January 16, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; transcript included. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1794 January 24, ALS, 1 p.; docketed.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4501
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1794 March 6, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #5718-d
- James Monroe about the Jacobins 1794 November 7, AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2119-a
- James Monroe to Citizen Otto 1794 November 18, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4909
- James Monroe to [Fulwar] Skipwith, Re: Haven 1795 January 1, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8707-a
- James Monroe to [John Henry Purviance] 1795 January 18, AL, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #8739-a
- John Jay to James Monroe 1795 February 5, ALS, 4 p. on 2 l. with address leaf; docketed; transcript and summary included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #2196
- Robert Brooke to James Monroe 1795 February 6, ALS, 2 p. on 2 l. with address leaf; docketed; photocopy. (Box 1)
  #7289-b
- James Monroe to the Committee of Public Safety 1795 July 14, ALS (draft), 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #5320
- James Monroe to Minister of Exterior Relations 1795 December 2, LS (unidentified hand), 3 p. on 1 l.; Monroe's wax seal on p. 3. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to [Timothy Pickering] as duplicate 1796 March 25, LS (official duplicate), 4 p. on 1 l.; docketed; transcript and summary included. (Box 1)
  #2362-d
- James Monroe to Benjamin F. Bache 1797 November 13, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; summary included. (Box 1)
  #2119
- James Monroe to Colonel Wilson C. Nicholas 1798 May 1, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #5533-a
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1799 February 9, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #9510
- Land grant to Henry Umbarger, signed by James Monroe 1800 February 15, DS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #2854
- John Blair to James Monroe 1800 May 20, ALS, 3 p. on 2 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4384
- James Monroe to Colonel Wilson C. Nicholas 1800 June 18, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Peter Carr 1800 August 19, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. Tracy W. McGregor Library (Box 1)
  #1231
- James Monroe Commission to Matthew Hanna 1800 September 12, DS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #309
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1800 December 25, DS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #1532
- William Hull on Monroe's house in Paris 1801 February 8, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- Cover to Court of Henrico County 1801 March 23, Address leaf only; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4776
- James Monroe Account to Edmund Randolph 1801 March 24, ADS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #5533-c
- James Monroe to [Wilson Cary Nicholas] 1801 April 6, ALS, 2 p. (Box 1)
  Monroe apologizes for replying so late and then says that he hopes that he will be able to provide the requested money but is not sure where he would be able to find the funds to do so.
  #1397
- James Monroe to [James Madison] 1801 May 17, ALS, 3 p on 2 l.; Barrow. Also includes James Monroe on James Thomson Callendar AD, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #8005
- Military Appointment of George Wilson, signed by Governor James Monroe 1801 May 28, AD, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #7792
- Appointment of William Dunlop to Captain 1801 October 27, DS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Creed Taylor 1802 February 1, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #1398
- James Monroe to William B. Giles 1802 February 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 leaf; with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #13915
- James Monroe to [Thomas Jefferson] 1802 March 18, LS, 1 p.; photocopy. (Box 1)
  Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. #4776-a
- James Monroe letter regarding the Virginia-Tennessee boundary 1802 May 20, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #38-550
- James Monroe to Charles F. Mercer 1802 June 17, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7650
- James Monroe to Col. Francis Walker 1802 August 28, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #3098
- James Monroe to Andrew Elliot 1802 September 10, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #2988
- Land Grant to Jehu Stephens by James Monroe 1802 September 27, AS, 2 p. on 2 l.; photocopy. Original privately owned. (Box 1)
- James Monroe's recommendation for Peter de Rieux 1802 November 2, ADS, 2 p. on 2 l.; copy; Barrow; damaged. (Box 1)
  #2447
- Bill drawn by Governor James Monroe during the session of Assembly 1802 December, AM, 3 p. on 2 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to General John Mason 1803 March 3, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
- John Page to James Monroe 1803 October 17, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #7326
- James Monroe to C[harles] F[enton] Mercer1803 October 22, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #10631
- James Monroe to J[ohn] H[enry] Purviance1804 August 27, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Joseph Cabell 1804 September 27, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #2529
- James Monroe to [John Henry Puviance] 1804 October 30, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Thomas Swan 1804 December 20, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5845
- James Monroe to George Joy 1805 August 28, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
  #2598
- James Monroe to [John Henry Purviance] 1806 January 2, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to John Henry Purviance 1806 January 7, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to John Henry Purviance 1806 January 8, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to John Henry Purviance 1806 January 10, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Mr. Chancellor [Creed Taylor] [1806 June], AL, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8481
- James Monroe to Sullivan 1806 August 29, AL, 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #7299
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1807 July 30, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; transcript included. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Walter Jones 1808 January 24, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5106
- James Monroe to Mr. Gilman 1808 March 25, ALS (draft), 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5412
- James Monroe to Creed Taylor [ca. 1808], ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- Memorandum of James Monroe 1808-1812, AD, 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #1331
- James Monroe to William Tudor Jr. 1809 January 17, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #1714
- James Monroe to Wilson Cary Nicholas 1809 June 19, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. with address on verso of p. 3; damaged, affecting some text, closing, and Monroe's signature on p. 3; remnants of wax seal. (Box 1)
  #5533-n
- James Monroe to Thomas Swan 1809 June 20, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4559
- James Monroe to [Henry?] Lee 1809 July 11, AL, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #7929
- James Monroe to Charles Fenton Mercer 1809 November 6, AL, 3 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #6691
- James Monroe to Dr. Charles Everett 1809 December 28, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4619
- James Monroe to Dr. [Charles Everett] 1810 January 13, ALS, 3 p. on 2 l.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to John Randolph 1810 June 15, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #3339
- James Monroe to Chancellor Taylor [Creed Taylor] 1811 January 21, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #1232
- James Monroe to Landon Carter 1811 June 17, Typed transcript. (Box 1)
  #38-486
- James Monroe to "Dear Sir" 1811 September 19, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #6691-a
- James Monroe to John Randolph 1811 November ?, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5842
- James Monroe to the Marshall of District of Maine 1811 December 27, LS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #5239
- Charles Fenton Mercer to James Monroe 1812 February 24, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7308
- James Monroe to Mr. Gerry 1813 January 1, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #5383-a
- James Monroe to Sir John Borlase Warren 1813 April 16, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1813 May 15, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #6697
- Creed Taylor to Colonel James Monroe 1813 May 24, ALS (copy), 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1813 September 4, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4748
- James Monroe to Mr. [Joseph] Delaplaine 1813 December 2, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow (Box 1)
  #5951
- James Monroe to A. J. Dallas 1814 January 30, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7102
- Draft of comments by James Monroe on War of 1812 [1814 January], AMs, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
  #2315
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1814 May 3, ALS, 3 p. on 2 l.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #6569
- James Monroe to [Charles Everett] 1814 June 2, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #1564
- James Monroe, commission as Bearer of Despatches to John Henry Purviance 1814 October 5, ADS (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Gov. W. Blount 1814 October 10, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #3699
- James Monroe to John H[enry] Purviance 1814 October 19, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to Peter Early 1814 October 20, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 1)
  #2288
- James Monroe to Andrew Jackson 1815 February 5, ALS, 3 p. on 3 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #3930
- James Monroe to [Alexander] Dallas 1815 February 15, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #2832-b
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1815 May 24, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #5077
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1815 July 8, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed.; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1815 July 22, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #3800
- James Monroe to Henry Jackson 1815 October 12, LS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #6995
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1815 November 12, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4188
- James Monroe to Craven Peyton 1816 March 30, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #9737-c
- James Monroe to [Stephen Pleasants or Richard Smith] 1816 September 30, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James W. Moss to James Monroe 1816 December 6, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #8807-a
- James Monroe account of Mr. Medley 1816, AMs, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Two memoranda re Nomination in caucus of Monroe for presidency [1816], both: AD, 1 p.; both in hand of Henry Clay. (Box 1)
  #3248
- James Monroe to Major W[illiam] Noland 1817 February 25, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #2718
- James Monroe to Thomas Swann 1817 April 26, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7455
- James Monroe to Byrd Willis 1817 May 17, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8800
- D. Lenox, President of the Pennsylvania Society of the Cincinnati, to James Monroe [1817?], DS, 1 p., with attached blank leaf; docketed (Box 1)
  #8685
- Documents relating to Monroe's Albemarle Lands: Limestone 1817-1818, Typed transcripts. (Box 1)
  #4509
- Holograph notes of James Monroe on fiscal and foreign affairs 1817-1824, AMs, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #6691-b
- James Monroe to William Benton 1818 January 3, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #7499
- James Monroe to David Higginbotham 1818 February 4, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. Also includes David Higginbotham to James Monroe, April 1818, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #3537
- James Johnson to James Monroe 1818 February 11, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- [Nicolas Biddle] to James Monroe 1818 February 25, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #2717
- [Nicolas Biddle] to James Monroe 1818 March 6, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Nicolas Biddle to James Monroe 1818 April 5, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- James Monroe to William Benton 1818 April 27, ALS, 2 p. on 2 l. with address leaf; docketed; photocopy. Original privately owned. (Box 1)
  #8669
- James Monroe to [overseer at Oak Hill?] 1818 May 22, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [William Benton] 1818 August 14, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 2)
  #2360
- James Monroe to [James Dinsmore] 1818 September 18, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf. (Box 2)
  #10428-f
- Nicolas Biddle to James Monroe 1818 September 28, ALS, l p. (Box 2)
- Nicolas Biddle to James Monroe 1818 October 19, ALS, 5 p. on 2 l. (Box 2)
- Jonathon Roberts to James Monroe 1818 November 22, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to James Madison 1818 December 23, AL, 1 p. with partial address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to Nicolas Biddle 1819 January 24, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [John C. Calhoun] 1819 September 20, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
  #4926
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1819 November 13, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #4830
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient]1819 December 20, ALS, 3 p. on 3 l.; docketed. Photocopy. Original privately owned. (Box 2)
  #9382
- James Monroe re Court martial of Midshipman Campbell 1820 January 1, ADS, 1 p. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 2)
- William Wirt to James Monroe 1820 April 22, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #5009
- William Wirt to [James Monroe] 1820 May 20, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #8700
- James Monroe to John C. Calhoun 1820 June, ALS, 4 p. on 4 l.; photocopy. Original privately owned. (Box 2)
  #8689
- James Monroe to Assistant Secretary of War 1820? September 29, ALS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #2598-a
- James Monroe to [Major Noland] 1820 October 29, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to William Wirt 1821 January 30, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #2134
- Abr[aha]m Eustis to Col. James Gadsden 1821 October 2, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l., with address leaf; ANS, n.d., James Monroe, on address leaf (Box 2)
  #4832
- James Monroe to [Eliza Monroe Hay] 1821 October 16, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
- Charles J. Nourse to Secretary of War 1822 May 29, ALS, 1 p.; ANS, n.d., James Monroe on verso (Box 2)
  #3490-a
- James Monroe to "Dear Sir" 1822 July 18, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to Overseer 1822 August 12, ALS, 4 p. on 2 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #3957
- James Monroe to Hugh Nelson 1823 May 11, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #38-304
- James Monroe to Thomas Miller 1823 June 23, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #8557
- James Monroe to John Brockenbrough, Jr. 1823 June 25, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #1921-a
- James Monroe to George Sullivan 1823 August 20, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- Notes on the State of the Union by James Monroe [ca. 1823?], AMs, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
  #2019-a
- James Monroe to Albert Gallatin [ca. 1823], AN, 1 p. with address leaf. (Box 2)
  #3643
- James Monroe to Major Noland 1824 March 17, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- Richard Rush to James Monroe 1824 March 20, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 2)
  #9119
- James Monroe to Major William Noland 1824 April 5, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf. (Box 2)
- Lewis Cass to James Monroe 1824 April 22, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #5476
- Hugh Henry Brackenridge to James Monroe 1824 November 13, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #7530-b
- Hugh Nelson to [James Monroe] 1824 November 22, ALS, 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
  #4970
- Monroe's Observations on claims against the United States[1825 January 5], ALS, 58 p.; partial transcript included; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [unidentifed recipient] 1825 February 28, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; transcript included; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #5853-b
- James Monroe to [unidentifed recipient] 1825 April 16, ALS, 1 p.; silked. (Box 2)
  #860
- James Monroe to Dr. Charles Everett 1825 July 10, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to Robert Y. Hayne 1825 August 1, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #6073
- James Monroe to [Samuel Southard?] 1825 August 16, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 2)
  #2474
- James Monroe to George Carter 1825 August 16, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1825 December 14, ALS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #8107
- James Monroe to Charles Fenton Mercer 1826 February 1, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to Richard Rush 1826 February 14, LS, 1 p. with address leaf. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1826 May 17, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [unidentified recipient] 1826 June 30, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #7678
- Tench Ringgold to Gen. Robert Swartout containing statement of James Monroe's finances 1826 September 14, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #8063
- James Monroe to Thomas Mann Randolph 1826 December 12, ALS, 3 p. on 1 l. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- Minutes of meetings of the Board of Visitors 1826-1827, Ds. (Box 2)
  The minutes for December 1826 are titled "Proceedings of the Board of Visitors December 1826" and are initialed by Monroe on the front cover. The minutes for July 1827 are titled "Proceedings of the Rector and Visitors July 1827" and are docketed by Monroe on the rear cover. Both are in the hand of Nicholas P. Trist.
  #RG-1/1/1.481
- James Monroe to [James H. Causten] 1827 January 30, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Monroe to [James Madison] 1827 May 30, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; photocopy. Original in James Madison Papers. (Box 2)
  #11946
- Col. S. Thayer to His Excellency James Monroe 1827 June 23, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
  #11945-a
- J.T. Kirkland to [James Monroe] 1827 June 27, ALS, 3 p.; docketed; silked. (Box 2)
  #11943-a